<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ipums-ddi-xslt.xsl"?>
<codeBook ID="ddi2-cdcfc570-3a3f-013c-327d-0242ac1c0004-cps_00004.dat-cps.ipums.org" version="2.5" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 http://www.ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>Codebook for an IPUMS CPS Data Extract</titl>
        <subTitl>DDI 2.5 metadata describing the extract file  'cps_00004.dat'</subTitl>
        <IDNo>ddi2-cdcfc570-3a3f-013c-327d-0242ac1c0004-cps_00004.dat-cps.ipums.org</IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="IPUMS" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">IPUMS</producer>
        <prodDate date="2023-11-26">November 26, 2023</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact URI="https://ipums.org" affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</contact>
      </distStmt>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>User Extract cps_00004.dat</titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer abbr="IPUMS" affiliation="University of Minnesota" role="Documentation">IPUMS</producer>
        <prodDate date="2023-11-26">November 26, 2023</prodDate>
        <prodPlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</prodPlac>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact URI="https://ipums.org" affiliation="University of Minnesota">IPUMS</contact>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName abbr="cps">IPUMS CPS</serName>
        <serInfo>DOI:10.18128/D030.V11.0</serInfo>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2023-11-26"/>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Geographic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Migration Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Health Insurance Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
        <topcClas vocab="IPUMS">Job Tenure &amp; Occupational Mobility Supplement Variables -- PERSON</topcClas>
      </subject>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3001">
        <timePrd date="2022-01" event="single">2022-01</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3002">
        <timePrd date="2022-02" event="single">2022-02</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3003">
        <timePrd date="2022-03" event="single">2022-03</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3010">
        <timePrd date="2022-03" event="single">2022-03</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3005">
        <timePrd date="2022-04" event="single">2022-04</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3006">
        <timePrd date="2022-05" event="single">2022-05</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3007">
        <timePrd date="2022-06" event="single">2022-06</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3008">
        <timePrd date="2022-07" event="single">2022-07</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3009">
        <timePrd date="2022-08" event="single">2022-08</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3011">
        <timePrd date="2022-09" event="single">2022-09</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3012">
        <timePrd date="2022-10" event="single">2022-10</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3013">
        <timePrd date="2022-11" event="single">2022-11</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <sumDscr ID="sdatref-3014">
        <timePrd date="2022-12" event="single">2022-12</timePrd>
        <nation abbr="us">United States</nation>
      </sumDscr>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, January 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, February 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, March 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, ASEC 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, April 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, May 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, June 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, July 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, August 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, September 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, October 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, November 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
      <notes><![CDATA[Additional notes on a sample that is part of this study:  IPUMS-CPS, December 2022
            Density of the full data file:  0.01%
            Density of this extract: 0.0%
]]></notes>
    </stdyInfo>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <confDec required="no"><![CDATA[None]]></confDec>
        <contact URI="http://cps.ipums.org/" affiliation="IPUMS">IPUMS CPS</contact>
        <citReq><![CDATA[Publications and research reports based on the IPUMS CPS database must cite it appropriately. The citation should include the following:

Sarah Flood, Miriam King, Renae Rodgers, Steven Ruggles, J. Robert Warren, Daniel Backman, Annie Chen, Grace Cooper, Stephanie Richards, Megan Schouweiler and Michael Westberry. IPUMS CPS: Version 11.0 [dataset]. Minneapolis, MN: IPUMS, 2023. https://doi.org/10.18128/D030.V11.0

The licensing agreement for use of IPUMS CPS data requires that users supply us with the title and full citation for any publications, research reports, or educational materials making use of the data or documentation. Please add your citation to the IPUMS bibliography: http://bibliography.ipums.org/]]></citReq>
        <conditions><![CDATA[Users of IPUMS CPS data must agree to abide by the conditions of use. A user's license is valid for one year and may be renewed.  Users must agree to the following conditions:

(1) No fees may be charged for use or distribution of the data.  All persons are granted a limited license to use these data, but you may not charge a fee for the data if you distribute it to others.

(2) Cite IPUMS appropriately.  For information on proper citation,  refer to the citation requirement section of this DDI document.

(3) Tell us about any work you do using the IPUMS.  Publications, research  reports, or presentations making use of IPUMS CPS should be added to our  Bibliography. Continued funding for the IPUMS depends on our ability to  show our sponsor agencies that researchers are using the data for productive  purposes.

(4) Use it for GOOD -- never for EVIL.]]></conditions>
        <disclaimer>The user of the data acknowledges that the original collector of the data, the authorized distributor of the data, and the relevant funding agency bear no responsibility for use of the data or for interpretations or inferences based upon such uses.</disclaimer>
      </useStmt>
    </dataAccs>
    <notes><![CDATA[User-provided description:  0004]]></notes>
    <notes>This extract is a revision of the user's previous extract, ID 14219249.</notes>
  </stdyDscr>
  <fileDscr ID="ExtractData">
    <fileTxt>
      <fileName>cps_00004.dat</fileName>
      <fileCont>Microdata records</fileCont>
      <fileStrc type="rectangular"/>
      <fileType charset="ISO-8859-1">ISO-8859-1 data file</fileType>
      <format>fixed length fields</format>
      <filePlac>IPUMS, 50 Willey Hall, 225 - 19th Avenue South, Minneapolis, MN 55455</filePlac>
    </fileTxt>
  </fileDscr>
  <dataDscr><var ID="YEAR" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="YEAR">
  <location EndPos="4" StartPos="1" width="4"/>
  <labl>Survey year</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[YEAR reports the year in which the survey was conducted.  YEARP is repeated on person records.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesYEAR is a 4-digit numeric value.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="SERIAL" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="SERIAL">
  <location EndPos="9" StartPos="5" width="5"/>
  <labl>Household serial number</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[SERIAL is an identifying number unique to each household in a given survey month and year.  All person records are assigned the same serial number as the household record they follow.  A combination of YEAR, MONTH, and SERIAL provides a within-sample unique identifier for every household in IPUMS-CPS; YEAR, MONTH, SERIAL, and PERNUM uniquely identify every person within a single sample.

SERIAL is a new value generated for IPUMS-CPS and should not be confused with the household serial number created by the Census Bureau and included in the original CPS data.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesSERIAL is a 5-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="MONTH" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="MONTH">
  <location EndPos="11" StartPos="10" width="2"/>
  <labl>Month</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[MONTH indicates the calendar month of the CPS interview.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>January</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>February</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>March</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>April</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>05</catValu>
    <labl>May</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>06</catValu>
    <labl>June</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>July</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>08</catValu>
    <labl>August</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>September</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>October</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>11</catValu>
    <labl>November</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>December</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HWTFINL" dcml="4" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="HWTFINL">
  <location EndPos="21" StartPos="12" width="10"/>
  <labl>Household weight, Basic Monthly</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HWTFINL is a household-level weight that should be used to generate statistics about households. The CPS uses a complex stratified sampling scheme, and HWTFINL must be used to produce unbiased household-level statistics from IPUMS-CPS basic monthly samples. For analyses of March Annual Social and Economic (ASEC) data, researchers should use HWTSUPP (This variable was renamed. Please see this renaming scheme for more information.). For individual-level analyses, researchers should use WTFINL, WTSUPP, or EARNWT. 

HWTFINL generally has the same value as WTFINL for the household head or reference person. Vacant housing units and households that could not be interviewed due to residents' absence or refusal to participate have a value of zero in HWTFINL; such sampled units were included in the public use CPS data beginning in 1988.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesHWTFINL is a 10-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CPSID" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="CPSID">
  <location EndPos="35" StartPos="22" width="14"/>
  <labl>CPSID, household record</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[CPSID is an IPUMS-CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies households across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSID index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSID allows users to link a household record across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSID value based on a combination of household identifiers. CPSID will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MISH). In some cases, a household will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. CPSID Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSID is available elsewhere.

CPSID may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. Users should note that ASEC oversample households (as indicated by ASECOVERH) will always have a CPSID value of 0.

Users may also want to see CPSIDP for more information about linking individuals across time using a person-specific version of CPSID.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesCPSID is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="ASECFLAG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="ASECFLAG">
  <location EndPos="36" StartPos="36" width="1"/>
  <labl>Flag for ASEC</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[ASECFLAG indicates whether the respondent is part of the ASEC or the March Basic. This variable is useful for users who wish to distinguish ASEC and March Basic files in their extracts. See further information about the ASEC versus the March Basic Monthly Files.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>ASEC</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>March Basic</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="ASECWTH" dcml="4" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="ASECWTH">
  <location EndPos="47" StartPos="37" width="11"/>
  <labl>Annual Social and Economic Supplement Household weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[ASECWTH is a household-level weight that should be used to generate statistics about households in March Annual Social and Economic (ASEC) Supplement data. The CPS uses a complex stratified sampling scheme, and ASECWTH must be used to produce unbiased household-level statistics from the IPUMS-CPS ASEC data. For analyses of non-ASEC data, researchers should use HWTFINL. For individual-level analyses, researchers should use WTFINL, ASECWT, or EARNWT. 

ASECWTH generally has the same value as WTSUPP for the household head or reference person. Vacant housing units and households that could not be interviewed due to residents' absence or refusal to participate have a value of zero in HWTSUPP; such sampled units were included in the public use CPS data beginning in 1988. 

Estimates on the entire population are prepared by projecting forward the resident population from the last available census. These projections are derived by updating the demographic census data from a number of other data sources that account for death, births and net migration. About 3 years after every census (i.e. 2003 for the 2000 Census and 2013 for the 2010 Census), the Census Bureau updates its independent population control and provides a new weight for the relevant years.

Two important points should be noted here. First, the lag between when the Census is conducted and when the CPS weights are updated is about 3 years. While the Census data are being processed, the CPS files are made available using the weighting scheme from the US Census prior to the latest Census. Second, once the files are updated, the old weights become obsolete and are replaced in the IPUMS data extract system. Published estimates from the lag years that use the old weights are not always updated. For example, 2010 poverty estimates were released in ASEC using the 2000 population controls. Once the 2010 population controls were made available, IPUMS-CPS replaced the ASEC 2010, 2011, and 2012 weights that are based on the 2000 population control with weights that are based on the 2010 population controls.

IPUMS-CPS makes available only the most up-to-date weights. The old values are available here: Old SPM and Weights Values.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesASECWTH is a 10-digit numeric variable with four implied decimals.  That is, 1234567890 should be interpreted as 123456.7890.  The IPUMS command files automatically divide ASECWTH by 10,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="GQTYPE" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="GQTYPE">
  <location EndPos="49" StartPos="48" width="2"/>
  <labl>Household type</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[GQTYPE categorizes the household in terms of the family type, including indications of group quarters status.   Group quarters households are categorized further by either having families within the household or not.  Institutions such as college dorms or military barracks are examples of group quarters without families.  GQTYPE also differentiates between households with civilians and households in which either one or both spouses are in the Armed Forces.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>Non-interview household</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>Husband/wife primary family (neither Armed Forces)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>Husband/wife primary family (either/both Armed Forces)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>Unmarried civilian male - primary family householder</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>Unmarried civilian female - primary family householder</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>05</catValu>
    <labl>Primary family householder - respondent in Armed Forces, unmarried</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>06</catValu>
    <labl>Civilian male primary individual</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>07</catValu>
    <labl>Civilian female primary individual</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>08</catValu>
    <labl>Primary individual householder - respondent in Armed Forces</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>Group quarters with family</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>Group quarters without family</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Blank</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HHINTYPE" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HHINTYPE">
  <location EndPos="50" StartPos="50" width="1"/>
  <labl>Type of household</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HHINTYPE is a household-level variable indicating whether members of the household were interviewed and, if not, why no interview took place.  Type A nonresponse households represent housing units suitable for inclusion in the survey whose residents were not interviewed for reasons such as refusal to participate and temporary absence.  Type B nonresponse households were vacant or were occupied by persons ineligible for interview (e.g., institutionalized persons).  Type C nonresponse households were housing units that were demolished, converted to storage or business use, or included in the sample by mistake.

Sampling for the CPS is based on housing units (addresses) rather than persons.  For this reason, interviewers necessarily initially visit some unoccupied or uninhabitable dwellings.  Participation in the survey is voluntary, rather than required by law, and institutionalized persons are intentionally excluded.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Interview</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Type A non-interview</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Type B/C non-interview</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="REGION" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="REGION">
  <location EndPos="52" StartPos="51" width="2"/>
  <labl>Region and division</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[REGION identifies the region and division where the housing unit was located. Unless otherwise noted in the comparability discussion, states are recoded into the following 1990 regional and divisional classification system: 

1. Northeast Region
New England Division: Connecticut, Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island, Vermont

Middle Atlantic Division: New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania
2. Midwest (formerly North Central) Region
East North Central Division: Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Ohio, Wisconsin

West North Central Division: Iowa, Kansas, Minnesota, Missouri, Nebraska, North Dakota, South Dakota
3. South Region
South Atlantic Division: Delaware, District of Columbia, Florida, Georgia, Maryland, North Carolina, South Carolina, Virginia, West Virginia

East South Central Division: Alabama, Kentucky, Mississippi, Tennessee

West South Central Division: Arkansas, Louisiana , Oklahoma, Texas
4. West Region
Mountain Division: Arizona, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Utah, Wyoming

Pacific Division: Alaska, California, Hawaii, Oregon, Washington
]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>11</catValu>
    <labl>New England Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>Middle Atlantic Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>21</catValu>
    <labl>East North Central Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>22</catValu>
    <labl>West North Central Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>31</catValu>
    <labl>South Atlantic Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>32</catValu>
    <labl>East South Central Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>33</catValu>
    <labl>West South Central Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>41</catValu>
    <labl>Mountain Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>42</catValu>
    <labl>Pacific Division</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>State not identified</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Geographic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="STATEFIP" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="STATEFIP">
  <location EndPos="54" StartPos="53" width="2"/>
  <labl>State (FIPS code)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[STATEFIP identifies the household's state of residence, using the Federal Information Processing Standards (FIPS) coding scheme, which orders the states alphabetically.

In 1973-1975 ASEC samples, all households in the Anaheim-Santa Ana-Garden Grove, CA METAREA are coded as Michigan-Wisconsin for STATEFIP in the original data. As there is insufficient geographic information in the public use data to determine which variable is in error, this mistake has been left un-recoded.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>Alabama</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>Alaska</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>Arizona</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>05</catValu>
    <labl>Arkansas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>06</catValu>
    <labl>California</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>08</catValu>
    <labl>Colorado</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>09</catValu>
    <labl>Connecticut</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>Delaware</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>11</catValu>
    <labl>District of Columbia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>Florida</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>13</catValu>
    <labl>Georgia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>15</catValu>
    <labl>Hawaii</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>16</catValu>
    <labl>Idaho</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>17</catValu>
    <labl>Illinois</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>18</catValu>
    <labl>Indiana</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>19</catValu>
    <labl>Iowa</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>20</catValu>
    <labl>Kansas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>21</catValu>
    <labl>Kentucky</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>22</catValu>
    <labl>Louisiana</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>23</catValu>
    <labl>Maine</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>24</catValu>
    <labl>Maryland</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>25</catValu>
    <labl>Massachusetts</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>26</catValu>
    <labl>Michigan</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>27</catValu>
    <labl>Minnesota</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>28</catValu>
    <labl>Mississippi</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>29</catValu>
    <labl>Missouri</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>30</catValu>
    <labl>Montana</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>31</catValu>
    <labl>Nebraska</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>32</catValu>
    <labl>Nevada</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>33</catValu>
    <labl>New Hampshire</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>34</catValu>
    <labl>New Jersey</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>35</catValu>
    <labl>New Mexico</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>36</catValu>
    <labl>New York</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>37</catValu>
    <labl>North Carolina</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>38</catValu>
    <labl>North Dakota</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>39</catValu>
    <labl>Ohio</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>40</catValu>
    <labl>Oklahoma</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>41</catValu>
    <labl>Oregon</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>42</catValu>
    <labl>Pennsylvania</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>44</catValu>
    <labl>Rhode Island</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>45</catValu>
    <labl>South Carolina</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>46</catValu>
    <labl>South Dakota</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>47</catValu>
    <labl>Tennessee</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>48</catValu>
    <labl>Texas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>49</catValu>
    <labl>Utah</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>50</catValu>
    <labl>Vermont</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>51</catValu>
    <labl>Virginia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>53</catValu>
    <labl>Washington</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>54</catValu>
    <labl>West Virginia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>55</catValu>
    <labl>Wisconsin</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>56</catValu>
    <labl>Wyoming</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>61</catValu>
    <labl>Maine-New Hampshire-Vermont</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>65</catValu>
    <labl>Montana-Idaho-Wyoming</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>68</catValu>
    <labl>Alaska-Hawaii</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>69</catValu>
    <labl>Nebraska-North Dakota-South Dakota</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>70</catValu>
    <labl>Maine-Massachusetts-New Hampshire-Rhode Island-Vermont</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>71</catValu>
    <labl>Michigan-Wisconsin</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>72</catValu>
    <labl>Minnesota-Iowa</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>73</catValu>
    <labl>Nebraska-North Dakota-South Dakota-Kansas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>74</catValu>
    <labl>Delaware-Virginia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>75</catValu>
    <labl>North Carolina-South Carolina</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>76</catValu>
    <labl>Alabama-Mississippi</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>77</catValu>
    <labl>Arkansas-Oklahoma</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>78</catValu>
    <labl>Arizona-New Mexico-Colorado</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>79</catValu>
    <labl>Idaho-Wyoming-Utah-Montana-Nevada</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>80</catValu>
    <labl>Alaska-Washington-Hawaii</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>81</catValu>
    <labl>New Hampshire-Maine-Vermont-Rhode Island</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>83</catValu>
    <labl>South Carolina-Georgia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>84</catValu>
    <labl>Kentucky-Tennessee</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>85</catValu>
    <labl>Arkansas-Louisiana-Oklahoma</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>87</catValu>
    <labl>Iowa-N Dakota-S Dakota-Nebraska-Kansas-Minnesota-Missouri</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>88</catValu>
    <labl>Washington-Oregon-Alaska-Hawaii</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>89</catValu>
    <labl>Montana-Wyoming-Colorado-New Mexico-Utah-Nevada-Arizona</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>90</catValu>
    <labl>Delaware-Maryland-Virginia-West Virginia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>State not identified</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Geographic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="METRO" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="METRO">
  <location EndPos="55" StartPos="55" width="1"/>
  <labl>Metropolitan central city status</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[METRO indicates whether a household was located in a metropolitan area.  For households within metropolitan areas, METRO specifies whether the housing unit was inside or outside the central city of the metropolitan area.  Information on metropolitan status was added by the Census Bureau, rather than being directly collected from respondents.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>Not identifiable</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Not in metro area</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Central city</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Outside central city</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>Central city status unknown</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Missing/Unknown</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Geographic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="STATECENSUS" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="STATECENSUS">
  <location EndPos="57" StartPos="56" width="2"/>
  <labl>State (Census code)</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[STATECENSUS identifies the household's state of residence using Census state codes.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>11</catValu>
    <labl>Maine</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>New Hampshire</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>13</catValu>
    <labl>Vermont</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>14</catValu>
    <labl>Massachusetts</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>15</catValu>
    <labl>Rhode Island</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>16</catValu>
    <labl>Connecticut</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>19</catValu>
    <labl>Maine, New Hampshire, Vermont, Rhode Island</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>21</catValu>
    <labl>New York</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>22</catValu>
    <labl>New Jersey</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>23</catValu>
    <labl>Pennsylvania</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>31</catValu>
    <labl>Ohio</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>32</catValu>
    <labl>Indiana</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>33</catValu>
    <labl>Illinois</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>34</catValu>
    <labl>Michigan</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>35</catValu>
    <labl>Wisconsin</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>39</catValu>
    <labl>Michigan, Wisconsin</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>41</catValu>
    <labl>Minnesota</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>42</catValu>
    <labl>Iowa</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>43</catValu>
    <labl>Missouri</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>44</catValu>
    <labl>North Dakota</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>45</catValu>
    <labl>South Dakota</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>46</catValu>
    <labl>Nebraska</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>47</catValu>
    <labl>Kansas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>49</catValu>
    <labl>Minnesota, Iowa, Missouri, North Dakota, South Dakota, Nebraska, Kansas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>50</catValu>
    <labl>Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, West Virginia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>51</catValu>
    <labl>Delaware</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>52</catValu>
    <labl>Maryland</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>53</catValu>
    <labl>District of Columbia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>54</catValu>
    <labl>Virginia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>55</catValu>
    <labl>West Virginia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>56</catValu>
    <labl>North Carolina</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>57</catValu>
    <labl>South Carolina</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>58</catValu>
    <labl>Georgia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>59</catValu>
    <labl>Florida</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>60</catValu>
    <labl>South Carolina, Georgia</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>61</catValu>
    <labl>Kentucky</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>62</catValu>
    <labl>Tennessee</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>63</catValu>
    <labl>Alabama</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>64</catValu>
    <labl>Mississippi</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>67</catValu>
    <labl>Kentucky, Tennessee</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>69</catValu>
    <labl>Alabama, Mississippi</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>71</catValu>
    <labl>Arkansas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>72</catValu>
    <labl>Louisiana</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>73</catValu>
    <labl>Oklahoma</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>74</catValu>
    <labl>Texas</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>79</catValu>
    <labl>Arkansas, Louisiana, Oklahoma</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>81</catValu>
    <labl>Montana</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>82</catValu>
    <labl>Idaho</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>83</catValu>
    <labl>Wyoming</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>84</catValu>
    <labl>Colorado</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>85</catValu>
    <labl>New Mexico</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>86</catValu>
    <labl>Arizona</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>87</catValu>
    <labl>Utah</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>88</catValu>
    <labl>Nevada</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>89</catValu>
    <labl>Montana, Idaho, Wyoming, Colorado, New Mexico, Arizona, Utah, Nevada</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>91</catValu>
    <labl>Washington</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>92</catValu>
    <labl>Oregon</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>93</catValu>
    <labl>California</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>94</catValu>
    <labl>Alaska</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>95</catValu>
    <labl>Hawaii</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>Washington, Oregon, Alaska, Hawaii</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Geographic Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HHINCOME" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="HHINCOME">
  <location EndPos="65" StartPos="58" width="8"/>
  <labl>Total household income</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HHINCOME reports the total money income during the previous calendar year of all adult household members.  The amount should equal the sum of all household members' individual incomes as recorded in the IPUMS-CPS variable INCTOT.  The persons included were those present in the household at the time of the survey.  People who lived in the household during the previous year but were not still living there at the time of the survey are not included; household members who lived elsewhere during the previous year but had joined the household at the time of the survey are included.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[Codes99999999 = N.I.U. (Not in Universe).]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="PUBHOUS" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="PUBHOUS">
  <location EndPos="66" StartPos="66" width="1"/>
  <labl>Living in public housing</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PUBHOUS indicates whether the house, apartment, or mobile home is part of a government housing project for people with low incomes, commonly known as a "public housing project."

Participation in public housing is determined by two factors: program eligibility and the availability of housing. Income standards for initial and continuing occupancy vary across local housing authorities, although Federal guidelines set broad limits. Rental charges define net benefits and cannot exceed 30 percent of the family's or the individual's net monthly income. A public housing unit can be occupied by a family of two or more related persons or an individual who is handicapped, elderly, or displaced by urban renewal or natural disaster. 

An alternative form of housing assistance is rent subsidy, in which the rent for a housing unit is reduced because the Federal, state, or local government is paying part of the cost.  See (RENTSUB).
 
Households coded as "Yes" in PUBHOUS or RENTSUB were receiving housing assistance at the time of the ASEC survey.  The reference period for some other non-cash benefits is the preceding calendar year (for Food Stamps) or the previous six months (for heat subsidy). 

For some variables relating to means-tested government assistance, including PUBHOUS, information was collected only from households whose estimated income fell below a given threshold.  During the first month that a household entered the survey, and one year later, the CPS interviewer asked the respondent to estimate the family's total income in the past twelve months, by choosing one of fourteen broad categories.  Only households in which the household members' combined income fell below a given level (e.g., under 30,000 dollars in the 1980s) were questioned about means-tested program benefits.  Households with estimated incomes above the threshold were presumed to not qualify for or receive such benefits, and were not asked these questions, to limit the length of interviews.  Households that were not questioned were coded as "no" for several variables relating to the receipt of means-tested benefits, including PUBHOUS.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="RENTSUB" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="RENTSUB">
  <location EndPos="67" StartPos="67" width="1"/>
  <labl>Paying lower rent due to government subsidy</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[RENTSUB indicates whether the rent on the house, apartment or mobile home is reduced because a Federal, state or local government is paying part of the cost. With rent subsidies, the difference between the "fair market" rent and the rent charged to the tenant in private sector housing is paid to the owner by a government agency, using federal, state, or local funds.  See also (PUBHOUS) for information on public housing, an alternative form of housing assistance to low-income families and individuals. 

For some variables relating to means-tested government assistance, including RENTSUB, information was collected only from households whose estimated income fell below a given threshold.  During the first month that a household entered the survey, and one year later, the CPS interviewer asked the respondent to estimate the family's total income in the past twelve months, by choosing one of fourteen broad categories.  Only households in which the household members' combined income fell below a given level (e.g., under 30,000 dollars in the 1980s) were questioned about means-tested program benefits.  Households with estimated incomes above the threshold were presumed to not qualify for or receive such benefits, and were not asked these questions, to limit the length of interviews.  Households that were not questioned were coded as "no" for several variables relating to the receipt of means-tested benefits, including RENTSUB.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="FOODSTMP" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="FOODSTMP">
  <location EndPos="68" StartPos="68" width="1"/>
  <labl>Food stamp recipiency</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[FOODSTMP indicates whether one or more members of the household received benefits from the Supplement Nutrition Assistance Program (SNAP) during the prior year. This program is formerly known as the Food Stamps program.

Once such a household was identified, three follow-up questions were asked.  The first question determined the number of current household members covered by Food Stamps during the previous calendar year (STAMPNO).  The second question determined the number of months that Food Stamps were received during the previous year (STAMPMO).  Finally, a last question determined the total face value of Food Stamps received during that period (STAMPVAL).

The Food Stamp Act of 1977 was enacted to increase the food purchasing power of eligible households through the use of coupons to purchase food. The Food and Nutrition Service of the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) administers the Food Stamp Program through State and local welfare offices. The Food Stamp Program is the major national income support program which provides benefits to all low-income and low-resource households, regardless of the person's characteristics (e.g., sex, age, disability, etc.). The Food Stamps program was renamed SNAP as part of the Farm Bill of 2008.

For some variables relating to means-tested government assistance, including FOODSTMP, information was collected only from households whose estimated income fell below a given threshold.  During the first month that a household entered the survey, and one year later, the CPS interviewer asked the respondent to estimate the family's total income in the past twelve months, by choosing one of fourteen broad categories.  Only households in which the household members' combined income fell below a given level (e.g., under 30,000 dollars in the 1980s) were questioned about means-tested program benefits.  Households with estimated incomes above the threshold were presumed to neither qualify for nor receive such benefits, and were not asked these questions, to limit the length of interviews.  Households that were not questioned were coded as "no" for several variables relating to the receipt of means-tested benefits, including FOODSTMP.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="FAMINC" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="FAMINC">
  <location EndPos="71" StartPos="69" width="3"/>
  <labl>Family income of householder</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[FAMINC reports annual family income, in categories, of all persons related to the head of household/householder. For individuals who are not part of the householder's family, FAMINC reports the value for the householder's family. 

This measure includes the income of all members of the household who are 15 years of age or older.  Income includes money from jobs; net income from business, farm or rent; pensions; dividends; interest; Social Security payments; and any other monetary income received by family members.

Family income is collected as part of the basic monthly survey. At the end of the monthly labor force survey, respondents are asked to choose the category that represents the total combined income during the past 12 months for all members of the householder's family. The questionnaire says that "This includes money from jobs, net income from business, farm or rent, pensions, dividends, interest, social security payments and any other money income received" by members of the householder's family who are 15 years of age or older. Available categories change over time.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>100</catValu>
    <labl>Under $5,000</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>110</catValu>
    <labl>Under $1,000</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>111</catValu>
    <labl>Under $500</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>112</catValu>
    <labl>$500 - 999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>120</catValu>
    <labl>$1,000 - 1,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>121</catValu>
    <labl>$1,000 - 1,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>122</catValu>
    <labl>$1,500-1,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>130</catValu>
    <labl>$2,000 - 2,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>131</catValu>
    <labl>$2,000 - 2,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>132</catValu>
    <labl>$2,500 - 2,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>140</catValu>
    <labl>$3,000 - 3,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>141</catValu>
    <labl>$3,000 - 3,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>142</catValu>
    <labl>$3,500 - 3,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>150</catValu>
    <labl>$4,000 - 4,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>200</catValu>
    <labl>$5,000 - 7,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>210</catValu>
    <labl>$5,000 - 7,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>220</catValu>
    <labl>$5,000 - 5,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>230</catValu>
    <labl>$6,000 - 7,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>231</catValu>
    <labl>$6,000 - 7,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>232</catValu>
    <labl>$6,000 - 6,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>233</catValu>
    <labl>$7,000 - 7,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>234</catValu>
    <labl>$7,000 - 7,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>300</catValu>
    <labl>$7,500 - 9,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>310</catValu>
    <labl>$7,500 - 7,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>320</catValu>
    <labl>$8,000 - 8,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>330</catValu>
    <labl>$8,500 - 8,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>340</catValu>
    <labl>$8,000 - 8,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>350</catValu>
    <labl>$9,000 - 9,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>400</catValu>
    <labl>$10,000 - 14,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>410</catValu>
    <labl>$10,000 - 10,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>420</catValu>
    <labl>$11,000 - 11,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>430</catValu>
    <labl>$10,000 - 12,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>440</catValu>
    <labl>$10,000 - 11,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>450</catValu>
    <labl>$12,000 - 12,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>460</catValu>
    <labl>$12,000 - 14,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>470</catValu>
    <labl>$12,500 - 14,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>480</catValu>
    <labl>$13,000 - 13,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>490</catValu>
    <labl>$14,000 - 14,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>500</catValu>
    <labl>$15,000 - 19,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>510</catValu>
    <labl>$15,000 - 15,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>520</catValu>
    <labl>$16,000 - 16,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>530</catValu>
    <labl>$17,000 - 17,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>540</catValu>
    <labl>$15,000 - 17,499</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>550</catValu>
    <labl>$17,500 - 19,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>560</catValu>
    <labl>$18,000 - 19,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>600</catValu>
    <labl>$20,000 - 24,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>700</catValu>
    <labl>$25,000 - 49,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>710</catValu>
    <labl>$25,000 - 29,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>720</catValu>
    <labl>$30,000 - 34,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>730</catValu>
    <labl>$35,000 - 39,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>740</catValu>
    <labl>$40,000 - 49,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>800</catValu>
    <labl>$50,000 and over</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>810</catValu>
    <labl>$50,000 - 74,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>820</catValu>
    <labl>$50,000 - 59,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>830</catValu>
    <labl>$60,000 - 74,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>840</catValu>
    <labl>$75,000 and over</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>841</catValu>
    <labl>$75,000 - 99,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>842</catValu>
    <labl>$100,000 - 149,999</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>843</catValu>
    <labl>$150,000 and over</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>995</catValu>
    <labl>Missing</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>996</catValu>
    <labl>Refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>997</catValu>
    <labl>Don't know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>999</catValu>
    <labl>Blank</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Economic Characteristics Variables -- HOUSEHOLD</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="PERNUM" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="PERNUM">
  <location EndPos="73" StartPos="72" width="2"/>
  <labl>Person number in sample unit</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PERNUM numbers all persons within each household consecutively (starting with "1") in the order in which they are listed in the original CPS data.  When combined with YEAR , MONTH, and SERIAL, PERNUM uniquely identifies each person within IPUMS-CPS samples, though not across IPUMS-CPS samples.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesPERNUM is a 2-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="WTFINL" dcml="4" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="WTFINL">
  <location EndPos="87" StartPos="74" width="14"/>
  <labl>Final Basic Weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[WTFINL is the final person-level weight that should be used in analyses of basic monthly data. 

When analyzing ASEC data, researchers should use the person weight ASECWT. For analyses including the variables EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, and UNION, researchers should use the EARNWT variable. 

WTFINL is the second stage weight in CPS (see technical documentation). It is based on the inverse probability of selection into the sample and adjustments for the following factors: failure to obtain an interview; sampling within large sample units; adjustments to the known distribution of the entire population according to stage, age, sex, race, and Hispanic ethnicity; and allotting a weight of zero to populations not sampled in other monthly surveys (i.e., persons in the Hispanic oversample and members of the armed forces in ASEC samples).]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesWTFINL is a 14-digit numeric variable with four implied decimals.  That is, 12345678901234 should be interpreted as 1234567890.1234.  The IPUMS command files automatically make the necessary adjustment, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CPSIDV" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="CPSIDV">
  <location EndPos="102" StartPos="88" width="15"/>
  <labl>Validated Longitudinal Identifier</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[CPSIDV is an IPUMS CPS-created variable that uniquely identifies individuals across CPS samples. In addition to linking records across the CPS 4-8-4 rotation pattern, CPSIDV only makes links between those records whose SEX and RACE values do not change and whose AGE values change in expected ways over time. 

CPSIDV is based on CPSIDP and so there are some structural similarities between them. The first six digits of CPSIDV are identical to CPSIDP - the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. Like CPSIDP, CPSIDV allows users to link a respondent appearing with a designated household roster line number (LINENO) across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern. 

Only records that link using CPSIDP that also have consistent race and sex values and age values that increase at least one but not more than two years over the course of the 16-month CPS rotation are linkable using CPSIDV. As a result, linkage rates using CPSIDV are slightly lower than those achieved using CPSIDP. However, linkages created with CPSIDV do not require the recommended post-linking verification steps recommended for use with CPSIDP links. Users should note that original, unharmonized values of age, sex, and race are used in the creation of CPSIDV. The procedure and validation criteria for creating CPSIDV are described in detail in A Holistic Approach to Validating Current Population Survey Panel Data. 

CPSIDV may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. 

To get started using CPSIDV, users may want to sort their data file by CPSIDV and MISH to create a person-time file. 

Users should take care when including the March Basic or ASEC as part of their linking. Respondents who are part of the ASEC oversample (as indicated by ASECOVERP) have a CPSIDV value of 0. For further information about the relationship between the March Basic and the ASEC, please see our additional documentation.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesCPSIDV is a 15-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="CPSIDP" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="CPSIDP">
  <location EndPos="116" StartPos="103" width="14"/>
  <labl>CPSID, person record</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[CPSIDP is an IPUMS CPS defined variable that uniquely identifies individuals across CPS samples. The first six digits of CPSIDP index the four-digit year and two-digit month that the household was first in the CPS. CPSIDP allows users to link a respondent appearing with a designated household roster line number (LINENO) across samples, based on the 4-8-4 rotation pattern, by assigning a unique CPSIDP value to this line number. CPSIDP will only ever appear for a maximum of 8 times, which is the number of times a household may be observed in the CPS survey (as indexed by MISH). In some cases, individuals will appear fewer than 8 times due to migration, mortality, non-response, and recording errors. Extensive documentation about the creation of CPSIDP is available elsewhere.

Users should note that it is important to verify CPSIDP linkages with AGE, SEX, and RACE. In some cases CPSIDP will result in erroneous links, which are due to errors in the source data. Cases with the same CPSIDP value may also have inconsistent responses across samples due to errors on the part of the respondent or in recording the response. Ultimately, it is up to the individual researcher to determine the acceptability of the linkages made using CPSIDP. 

CPSIDP may also be used to link ASEC respondents who are in the March Basic Monthly file to other months of CPS data. This linking is made possible by IPUMS through the creation of MARBASECIDP. 

To get started using CPSIDP, users may want to sort their data file by CPSIDP and MISH to create a person-time file. 

Users should take care when including the March Basic or ASEC as part of their linking. Respondents who are part of the ASEC oversample (as indicated by ASECOVERP) have a CPSIDP value of 0. For further information about the relationship between the March Basic and the ASEC, please see our additional documentation.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesCPSIDP is a 14-digit numeric variable.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Linking Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="ASECWT" dcml="4" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="ASECWT">
  <location EndPos="127" StartPos="117" width="11"/>
  <labl>Annual Social and Economic Supplement Weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[ASECWT is a person-level weight that should be used in analyses of individual-level CPS supplement data. Since the CPS relies on a complex stratified sampling scheme, it is essential to use one of the provided weighting variables.

Researchers should use WTFINL rather than ASECWT when they wish to conduct person-level analyses of non-ASEC data. EARNWT should be used for any analysis including a small number of person-level variables (EARNWEEK, HOURWAGE, PAIDHOUR, and UNION). Researchers should use ASECWTH for household-level analyses. ASECWTCVD is available for the 2020 ASEC to adjust for nonrandom nonresponse resulting from the COVID-19 pandemic.

User Caution: For analyses that include the 2014 ASEC sample, please see the comparability tab.

The ASEC CPS files include two groups of people who are not included in the production of published labor force statistics: (1) members of the armed services, and (2) members of the Hispanic oversample who were interviewed in months other than March. WTFINL and EARNWT assign these groups a value of 0. Both groups are assigned non-zero values in ASECWT.

ASECWT is based on the inverse probability of selection into the sample and adjustments for the following factors: failure to obtain an interview; sampling within large sample units; the known distribution of the entire population according to age, sex, and race; over-sampling Hispanic persons; to give husbands and wives the same weight; and an additional step to provide consistency with labor force estimates from the basic survey. 

Estimates on the entire population are prepared by projecting forward the resident population from the last available census. These projections are derived by updating the demographic census data from a number of other data sources that account for death, births and net migration. About 3 years after every census (i.e. 2003 for the 2000 Census and 2013 for the 2010 Census), the Census Bureau updates its independent population control and provides a new weight for the relevant years.

Two important points should be noted here. First, the lag between when the Census is conducted and when the CPS weights are updated is about 3 years. While the Census data are being processed, the CPS files are made available using the weighting scheme from the US Census prior to the latest Census. Second, once the files are updated, the old weights become obsolete and are replaced in the IPUMS data extract system. Published estimates from the lag years that use the old weights are not always updated. For example, 2010 poverty estimates were released in ASEC using the 2000 population controls. Once the 2010 population controls were made available, IPUMS-CPS replaced the ASEC 2010, 2011, and 2012 weights that are based on the 2000 population control with weights that are based on the 2010 population controls. IPUMS-CPS makes available only the most up-to-date weights.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesASECWT is a 10-digit numeric variable with four implied decimal places. That is, values of 0012345600 should be interpreted as 1,234.56.  The IPUMS command files automatically divide ASECWT by 10,000, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Technical Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="YRIMMIG" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="YRIMMIG">
  <location EndPos="131" StartPos="128" width="4"/>
  <labl>Year of immigration</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[YRIMMIG reports the year in which a person born outside the United States "came to the U.S. to stay."

User Note: There are significant comparability issues in this variable after 1991. Please see the Comparability section for details.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0000</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1949</catValu>
    <labl>1949 or earlier</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1959</catValu>
    <labl>1950-1959</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1964</catValu>
    <labl>1960-1964</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1969</catValu>
    <labl>1965-1969</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1974</catValu>
    <labl>1970-1974</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1979</catValu>
    <labl>1975-1979</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1981</catValu>
    <labl>1980-1981</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1983</catValu>
    <labl>1982-1983</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1985</catValu>
    <labl>1984-1985</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1987</catValu>
    <labl>1986-1987</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1989</catValu>
    <labl>1988-1989</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1991</catValu>
    <labl>1990-1991</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1993</catValu>
    <labl>1992-1993</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1994</catValu>
    <labl>1992-1994</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1995</catValu>
    <labl>1994-1995</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1996</catValu>
    <labl>1994-1996</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1997</catValu>
    <labl>1996-1997</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1998</catValu>
    <labl>1996-1998 (2000 CPS: 1998)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1999</catValu>
    <labl>1998-1999 (1999 CPS: 1996-1999)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2000</catValu>
    <labl>1998-2000</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2001</catValu>
    <labl>2000-2001 (2001 CPS: 1998-2001)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2002</catValu>
    <labl>2000-2002</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2003</catValu>
    <labl>2002-2003 (2003 CPS: 2000-2003)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2004</catValu>
    <labl>2002-2004</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2005</catValu>
    <labl>2004-2005 (2005 CPS: 2002-2005)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2006</catValu>
    <labl>2004-2006</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2007</catValu>
    <labl>2004-2007</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2008</catValu>
    <labl>2006-2008 (2006-2007 CPS: 2004-2008)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2009</catValu>
    <labl>2006-2009 (2012 CPS forward: 2008-2009)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2010</catValu>
    <labl>2008-2010</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2011</catValu>
    <labl>2008-2011 (2014 CPS forward: 2010-2011)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2012</catValu>
    <labl>2010-2012</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2013</catValu>
    <labl>2010-2013 (2016 CPS forward: 2012-2013)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2014</catValu>
    <labl>2012-2014</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2015</catValu>
    <labl>2012-2015 (2018 CPS forward: 2014-2015)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2016</catValu>
    <labl>2014-2016</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2017</catValu>
    <labl>2014-2017 (2019 CPS forward: 2016-2017)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2018</catValu>
    <labl>2016-2018</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2019</catValu>
    <labl>2016-2019</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2020</catValu>
    <labl>2018-2020</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2021</catValu>
    <labl>2018-2021 (2022 CPS forward: 2018-2019)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2022</catValu>
    <labl>2020-2022</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Ethnicity/Nativity Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="EMPSTAT" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="EMPSTAT">
  <location EndPos="133" StartPos="132" width="2"/>
  <labl>Employment status</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[EMPSTAT indicates whether persons were part of the labor force--working or seeking work--and, if so, whether they were currently unemployed. The variable also provides information on the activity (e.g., doing housework, attending school,) or status (e.g., retired, unable to work) of persons not in the labor force, as well as limited additional information on those who are in the labor force (e.g. members of the Armed Forces, those with a job, but not at work last week). See LABFORCE for a dichotomous variable identifying whether a person participated in the labor force.

In the CPS, individuals' employment status was determined on the basis of answers to a series of questions relating to their activities during the preceding week.  Those who reported doing any work at all for pay or profit, or working at least fifteen hours without pay in a family business or farm, were classified as "at work."  Those who did not work during the previous week but who acknowledged having a job or business from which they were temporarily absent (e.g., due to illness, vacation, bad weather, or labor dispute) were also classified as employed, under the heading "has job, not at work last week."

Because the CPS is designed to measure unemployment in the civilian population, the original employment status variable in the survey classifies members of the armed forces as NIU (Not in universe).

Unemployed persons make up the third element of the labor force.  Individuals were coded as unemployed if they did no work for pay or profit, did not have a job from which they were briefly absent, and either reported looking for work as their major activity during the previous week (for 1962 through 1993) or answered yes to a question about whether they had been looking for work in the past four weeks. People who were temporarily laid off from a job were also classified as unemployed. A separate CPS variable specifying whether an unemployed person had worked before or was looking for a first job was used to distinguish between "experienced" and "inexperienced" unemployed persons in IPUMS CPS.

Persons who were neither employed nor unemployed fall into the residual category, "not in labor force."  Such individuals might be retired, disabled due to an illness lasting at least 6 months, occupied with other activities such as attending school or keeping house, or convinced that they are unlikely to find employment (discouraged workers).]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>Armed Forces</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>At work</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>12</catValu>
    <labl>Has job, not at work last week</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>20</catValu>
    <labl>Unemployed</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>21</catValu>
    <labl>Unemployed, experienced worker</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>22</catValu>
    <labl>Unemployed, new worker</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>30</catValu>
    <labl>Not in labor force</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>31</catValu>
    <labl>NILF, housework</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>32</catValu>
    <labl>NILF, unable to work</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>33</catValu>
    <labl>NILF, school</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>34</catValu>
    <labl>NILF, other</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>35</catValu>
    <labl>NILF, unpaid, lt 15 hours</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>36</catValu>
    <labl>NILF, retired</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="LABFORCE" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="LABFORCE">
  <location EndPos="134" StartPos="134" width="1"/>
  <labl>Labor force status</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[LABFORCE is a dichotomous variable indicating whether the respondent participated in the labor force during the preceding week.  See EMPSTAT for a more detailed employment status variable.   Those coded as "yes" in LABFORCE were either: were at work; held a job but were temporarily absent from work due to factors like vacation or illness; were seeking work; or were temporarily laid off from a job during the reference period.  

Because the CPS is designed to measure unemployment in the civilian population, the original dichotomous employment status variable in the survey classifies members of the armed forces as NIU (Not in universe).]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No, not in the labor force</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes, in the labor force</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="OCC" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="OCC">
  <location EndPos="138" StartPos="135" width="4"/>
  <labl>Occupation</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[OCC reports the person's primary occupation.  Respondents who held more than one job were to report the job at which they worked the largest number of hours.  For persons who were employed at the time of the survey, OCC relates to the job worked during the preceding week; unemployed persons and those not currently in the labor force were to give their most recent occupation.   The CPS interviewer collected information by asking what kind of work the person was doing, and Census Bureau staff coded the information into the contemporary CPS or census occupational classification.  Researchers who wish to work with a consistent occupational coding scheme for 1968 forward should use the OCC1950 variable.  For general discussion of employment concepts, including the definition of those not in the labor force, see the documentation on EMPSTAT.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesOCC is a 4-digit numeric variable.
(Codes for 1962-1967 are 2 digits; each is preceded by two zeros).
(Codes for 1968-2002 are 3 digits; each is preceded by a zero in the first position.)

1962-1967  
1968-1971
1972-1982
1983-1991
1992-2002
2003-2010
2011-2019
2020+]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Work Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="MIGRATE1" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="MIGRATE1">
  <location EndPos="139" StartPos="139" width="1"/>
  <labl>Migration status, 1 year</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[MIGRATE1 indicates whether the respondent had changed residence in the past year.   Those who were living in the same house as one year ago were considered non-movers and were asked no further questions about migration over the past year.   Movers were asked about the city, county and state and/or the U.S. territory or foreign country where they resided one year ago.

The category "Same house" includes both persons who did not move since the reference date (March 1 of the preceding year) and those who had moved and then returned to their earlier residence. Movers are subdivided into the following categories: those who had moved within the same county; those who had crossed county lines but stayed in the same state; those who those who had resided in a different state; and those who had migrated from abroad.

Information about the state where movers were living one year ago is available in the MIGSTA1 variable.  COUNTRY specifies the foreign country or U.S. territory of previous residence for those who migrated from abroad during the past year. 

In the 2002 ASEC sample, 54 children between the ages of 1 and 3 are coded as NIU in the original data and have been left unrecoded despite not being in line with the universe statement in the original documentation.

User Caution: Frequencies in the 1995 ASEC original CPS data are highly suspect and differ greatly from surrounding years.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>Same house</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Different house, place not reported</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>3</catValu>
    <labl>Moved within county</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>4</catValu>
    <labl>Moved within state, different county</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>5</catValu>
    <labl>Moved between states</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>6</catValu>
    <labl>Abroad</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>9</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Migration Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="PAIDGH" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="PAIDGH">
  <location EndPos="141" StartPos="140" width="2"/>
  <labl>Employer paid for group health plan</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[PAIDGH indicates whether an employer or union paid for all, part, or none of the cost of premiums for an employment-based group health insurance plan that the respondent was included in (i.e., was the policyholder for), during the previous calendar year.  For discussion of changes in the question wording about inclusion in employment-based health insurance, see INCLUGH.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>10</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>20</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>21</catValu>
    <labl>Yes, paid for part</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>22</catValu>
    <labl>Yes, paid for all</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Health Insurance Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HIMCARENW" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HIMCARENW">
  <location EndPos="142" StartPos="142" width="1"/>
  <labl>Current Medicare coverage</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HIMCAIDNW identifies persons who reported having Medicare coverage at the time of their interview.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Health Insurance Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HIMCARELY" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HIMCARELY">
  <location EndPos="143" StartPos="143" width="1"/>
  <labl>Covered by Medicare last year</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HIMCARELY indicates whether the respondent was covered by Medicare during the previous calendar year. The data in HIMCARELY were edited by the Census Bureau and assign Medicare coverage to some persons who did not report such health insurance during questioning.

For 1980-1987, information on health insurance coverage was collected only for persons age 15 and above. The CPS interviewer asked, "At any time during [the previous year], was anyone in this household covered by Medicare, the health insurance for persons 65 years old and over or persons with disabilities?" The Census Bureau edited the data to allot coverage (a "Yes" response in HIMCARELY) to all persons age 65 and older who reported income from Social Security. After 1988, the universe for Medicare recipients was still treated as persons age 15 and older, even though the survey generally focused on insurance coverage for all age groups.

Beginning in 1988, the question wording remained the same, but CPS interviewers directly collected information on insurance coverage for all household members, of all ages. Because the universe for Medicare coverage was treated as persons age 15 and older, this basic change in the phrasing of insurance-related questions had less effect on HIMCARELY than on other insurance-related variables.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>0</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Health Insurance Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="HIMCAIDNW" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="HIMCAIDNW">
  <location EndPos="144" StartPos="144" width="1"/>
  <labl>Current Medicaid, CHIP, or other means-tested coverage</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[HIMCAIDNW identifies persons who reported having Medicaid, CHIP, or other means-tested coverage at the time of their interview. Interviewers defined Medicaid as "the government assistance that pays for health care," and they mentioned both federal Medicaid programs and the Medicaid programs specific to the state where the household was located when collecting this information. CHIP provides insurance to eligible children through Medicaid and other programs administered by the states. The original CPS documentation gives no indication of what is included under "other means-tested coverage."

Medicaid pays for medical assistance to low-income families with dependent children and to aged, blind, or permanently and totally disabled individuals with incomes insufficient to meet the costs of medical services. The program became law in 1965.  Medicaid is administered by state agencies and is jointly funded by the federal, state, and, sometimes, local governments. Eligibility requirements for this means-tested program vary across states.  All recipients of Aid to Families with Dependent Children (AFDC) and most recipients of Supplemental Security Income (SSI) are eligible for Medicaid coverage.  In some states, other persons qualify, such as needy unemployed persons who have children and who are not receiving cash assistance, and medically needy persons whose income and assets are too low to cover their medical costs. Many Medicaid recipients are inmates of medical institutions, such as low-income elderly persons in nursing homes. Such institutionalized persons are not included in the CPS sample.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>1</catValu>
    <labl>No</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>2</catValu>
    <labl>Yes</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Health Insurance Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="JTYPE" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="JTYPE">
  <location EndPos="146" StartPos="145" width="2"/>
  <labl>Type of business or organization in which you worked last year</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[JTYPE identifies the type of private business the respondent is currently employed in.  

This variable is part of the Job Tenure Supplement.

Users should note that there are a number of cases that are coded as NIU though they meet the documented universe characteristics.  In each of these observations, JTCLASS is also NIU, so it could be that JTYPE requires a valid entry into JTOCC to be in universe.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>Manufacturing</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>Retail trade</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>03</catValu>
    <labl>Wholesale trade</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>04</catValu>
    <labl>Something else</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>96</catValu>
    <labl>Refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>97</catValu>
    <labl>Don't Know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>98</catValu>
    <labl>No response</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>99</catValu>
    <labl>NIU</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Job Tenure &amp; Occupational Mobility Supplement Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="JTOCC" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="JTOCC">
  <location EndPos="150" StartPos="147" width="4"/>
  <labl>Occupation one year ago</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[JTOCC reports the occupation code of the job the respondent was working one year ago.  

This variable is part of the Job Tenure Supplement.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesJTOCC is a 4-digit numeric variable.

1983-1991
1992-2002
2003-2010
2011+]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Job Tenure &amp; Occupational Mobility Supplement Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="JTOCC1990" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="JTOCC1990">
  <location EndPos="153" StartPos="151" width="3"/>
  <labl>Occupation one year ago, 1990 basis</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[JTOCC1990 recodes the variable JTOCC the occupation code of the job the respondent worked one year ago into the harmonized 1990 Census Bureau occupation classification system.  These codes are also comparable to the variable OCC1990.  

This variable is part of the Job Tenure Supplement.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>003</catValu>
    <labl>Legislators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>004</catValu>
    <labl>Chief executives and public administrators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>007</catValu>
    <labl>Financial managers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>008</catValu>
    <labl>Human resources and labor relations managers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>013</catValu>
    <labl>Managers and specialists in marketing, advertising, and public relations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>014</catValu>
    <labl>Managers in education and related fields</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>015</catValu>
    <labl>Managers of medicine and health occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>016</catValu>
    <labl>Postmasters and mail superintendents</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>017</catValu>
    <labl>Managers of food-serving and lodging establishments</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>018</catValu>
    <labl>Managers of properties and real estate</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>019</catValu>
    <labl>Funeral directors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>021</catValu>
    <labl>Managers of service organizations, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>022</catValu>
    <labl>Managers and administrators, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>023</catValu>
    <labl>Accountants and auditors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>024</catValu>
    <labl>Insurance underwriters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>025</catValu>
    <labl>Other financial specialists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>026</catValu>
    <labl>Management analysts</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>027</catValu>
    <labl>Personnel, HR, training, and labor relations specialists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>028</catValu>
    <labl>Purchasing agents and buyers, of farm products</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>029</catValu>
    <labl>Buyers, wholesale and retail trade</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>033</catValu>
    <labl>Purchasing managers, agents and buyers, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>034</catValu>
    <labl>Business and promotion agents</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>035</catValu>
    <labl>Construction inspectors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>036</catValu>
    <labl>Inspectors and compliance officers, outside construction</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>037</catValu>
    <labl>Management support occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>043</catValu>
    <labl>Architects</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>044</catValu>
    <labl>Aerospace engineer</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>045</catValu>
    <labl>Metallurgical and materials engineers, variously phrased</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>047</catValu>
    <labl>Petroleum, mining, and geological engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>048</catValu>
    <labl>Chemical engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>053</catValu>
    <labl>Civil engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>055</catValu>
    <labl>Electrical engineer</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>056</catValu>
    <labl>Industrial engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>057</catValu>
    <labl>Mechanical engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>059</catValu>
    <labl>Not-elsewhere-classified engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>064</catValu>
    <labl>Computer systems analysts and computer scientists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>065</catValu>
    <labl>Operations and systems researchers and analysts</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>066</catValu>
    <labl>Actuaries</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>067</catValu>
    <labl>Statisticians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>068</catValu>
    <labl>Mathematicians and mathematical scientists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>069</catValu>
    <labl>Physicists and astronomers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>073</catValu>
    <labl>Chemists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>074</catValu>
    <labl>Atmospheric and space scientists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>075</catValu>
    <labl>Geologists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>076</catValu>
    <labl>Physical scientists, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>077</catValu>
    <labl>Agricultural and food scientists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>078</catValu>
    <labl>Biological scientists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>079</catValu>
    <labl>Foresters and conservation scientists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>083</catValu>
    <labl>Medical scientists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>084</catValu>
    <labl>Physicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>085</catValu>
    <labl>Dentists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>086</catValu>
    <labl>Veterinarians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>087</catValu>
    <labl>Optometrists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>088</catValu>
    <labl>Podiatrists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>089</catValu>
    <labl>Other health and therapy</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>095</catValu>
    <labl>Registered nurses</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>096</catValu>
    <labl>Pharmacists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>097</catValu>
    <labl>Dietitians and nutritionists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>098</catValu>
    <labl>Respiratory therapists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>099</catValu>
    <labl>Occupational therapists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>103</catValu>
    <labl>Physical therapists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>104</catValu>
    <labl>Speech therapists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>105</catValu>
    <labl>Therapists, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>106</catValu>
    <labl>Physicians' assistants</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>113</catValu>
    <labl>Earth, environmental, and marine science instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>114</catValu>
    <labl>Biological science instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>115</catValu>
    <labl>Chemistry instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>116</catValu>
    <labl>Physics instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>118</catValu>
    <labl>Psychology instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>119</catValu>
    <labl>Economics instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>123</catValu>
    <labl>History instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>125</catValu>
    <labl>Sociology instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>127</catValu>
    <labl>Engineering instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>128</catValu>
    <labl>Math instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>139</catValu>
    <labl>Education instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>145</catValu>
    <labl>Law instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>147</catValu>
    <labl>Theology instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>149</catValu>
    <labl>Home economics instructors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>150</catValu>
    <labl>Humanities profs/instructors, college, nec</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>154</catValu>
    <labl>Subject instructors (HS/college)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>155</catValu>
    <labl>Kindergarten and earlier school teachers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>156</catValu>
    <labl>Primary school teachers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>157</catValu>
    <labl>Secondary school teachers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>158</catValu>
    <labl>Special education teachers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>159</catValu>
    <labl>Teachers , n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>163</catValu>
    <labl>Vocational and educational counselors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>164</catValu>
    <labl>Librarians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>165</catValu>
    <labl>Archivists and curators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>166</catValu>
    <labl>Economists, market researchers, and survey researchers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>167</catValu>
    <labl>Psychologists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>168</catValu>
    <labl>Sociologists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>169</catValu>
    <labl>Social scientists, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>173</catValu>
    <labl>Urban and regional planners</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>174</catValu>
    <labl>Social workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>175</catValu>
    <labl>Recreation workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>176</catValu>
    <labl>Clergy and religious workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>178</catValu>
    <labl>Lawyers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>179</catValu>
    <labl>Judges</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>183</catValu>
    <labl>Writers and authors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>184</catValu>
    <labl>Technical writers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>185</catValu>
    <labl>Designers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>186</catValu>
    <labl>Musician or composer</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>187</catValu>
    <labl>Actors, directors, producers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>188</catValu>
    <labl>Art makers: painters, sculptors, craft-artists, and print-makers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>189</catValu>
    <labl>Photographers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>193</catValu>
    <labl>Dancers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>194</catValu>
    <labl>Art/entertainment performers and related</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>195</catValu>
    <labl>Editors and reporters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>198</catValu>
    <labl>Announcers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>199</catValu>
    <labl>Athletes, sports instructors, and officials</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>200</catValu>
    <labl>Professionals, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>203</catValu>
    <labl>Clinical laboratory technologies and technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>204</catValu>
    <labl>Dental hygenists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>205</catValu>
    <labl>Health record tech specialists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>206</catValu>
    <labl>Radiologic tech specialists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>207</catValu>
    <labl>Licensed practical nurses</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>208</catValu>
    <labl>Health technologists and technicians, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>213</catValu>
    <labl>Electrical and electronic (engineering) technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>214</catValu>
    <labl>Engineering technicians, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>215</catValu>
    <labl>Mechanical engineering technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>217</catValu>
    <labl>Drafters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>218</catValu>
    <labl>Surveyors, cartographers, mapping scientists and technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>223</catValu>
    <labl>Biological technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>224</catValu>
    <labl>Chemical technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>225</catValu>
    <labl>Other science technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>226</catValu>
    <labl>Airplane pilots and navigators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>227</catValu>
    <labl>Air traffic controllers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>228</catValu>
    <labl>Broadcast equipment operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>229</catValu>
    <labl>Computer software developers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>233</catValu>
    <labl>Programmers of numerically controlled machine tools</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>234</catValu>
    <labl>Legal assistants, paralegals, legal support, etc</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>235</catValu>
    <labl>Technicians, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>243</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors and proprietors of sales jobs</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>253</catValu>
    <labl>Insurance sales occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>254</catValu>
    <labl>Real estate sales occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>255</catValu>
    <labl>Financial services sales occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>256</catValu>
    <labl>Advertising and related sales jobs</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>258</catValu>
    <labl>Sales engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>274</catValu>
    <labl>Salespersons, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>275</catValu>
    <labl>Retail sales clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>276</catValu>
    <labl>Cashiers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>277</catValu>
    <labl>Door-to-door sales, street sales, and news vendors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>283</catValu>
    <labl>Sales demonstrators / promoters / models</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>290</catValu>
    <labl>Sales workers--allocated (1990 internal census)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>303</catValu>
    <labl>Office supervisors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>308</catValu>
    <labl>Computer and peripheral equipment operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>313</catValu>
    <labl>Secretaries</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>314</catValu>
    <labl>Stenographers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>315</catValu>
    <labl>Typists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>316</catValu>
    <labl>Interviewers, enumerators, and surveyors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>317</catValu>
    <labl>Hotel clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>318</catValu>
    <labl>Transportation ticket and reservation agents</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>319</catValu>
    <labl>Receptionists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>323</catValu>
    <labl>Information clerks, nec</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>326</catValu>
    <labl>Correspondence and order clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>328</catValu>
    <labl>Human resources clerks, except payroll and timekeeping</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>329</catValu>
    <labl>Library assistants</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>335</catValu>
    <labl>File clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>336</catValu>
    <labl>Records clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>337</catValu>
    <labl>Bookkeepers and accounting and auditing clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>338</catValu>
    <labl>Payroll and timekeeping clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>343</catValu>
    <labl>Cost and rate clerks (financial records processing)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>344</catValu>
    <labl>Billing clerks and related financial records processing</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>345</catValu>
    <labl>Duplication machine operators / office machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>346</catValu>
    <labl>Mail and paper handlers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>347</catValu>
    <labl>Office machine operators, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>348</catValu>
    <labl>Telephone operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>349</catValu>
    <labl>Other telecom operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>354</catValu>
    <labl>Postal clerks, excluding mail carriers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>355</catValu>
    <labl>Mail carriers for postal service</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>356</catValu>
    <labl>Mail clerks, outside of post office</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>357</catValu>
    <labl>Messengers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>359</catValu>
    <labl>Dispatchers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>361</catValu>
    <labl>Inspectors, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>364</catValu>
    <labl>Shipping and receiving clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>365</catValu>
    <labl>Stock and inventory clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>366</catValu>
    <labl>Meter readers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>368</catValu>
    <labl>Weighers, measurers, and checkers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>373</catValu>
    <labl>Material recording, scheduling, production, planning, and expediting clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>375</catValu>
    <labl>Insurance adjusters, examiners, and investigators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>376</catValu>
    <labl>Customer service reps, investigators and adjusters, except insurance</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>377</catValu>
    <labl>Eligibility clerks for government programs; social welfare</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>378</catValu>
    <labl>Bill and account collectors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>379</catValu>
    <labl>General office clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>383</catValu>
    <labl>Bank tellers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>384</catValu>
    <labl>Proofreaders</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>385</catValu>
    <labl>Data entry keyers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>386</catValu>
    <labl>Statistical clerks</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>387</catValu>
    <labl>Teacher's aides</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>389</catValu>
    <labl>Administrative support jobs, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>390</catValu>
    <labl>Professional, technical, and kindred workers--allocated (1990 internal census)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>391</catValu>
    <labl>Clerical and kindred workers--allocated (1990 internal census)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>405</catValu>
    <labl>Housekeepers, maids, butlers, stewards, and lodging quarters cleaners</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>407</catValu>
    <labl>Private household cleaners and servants</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>408</catValu>
    <labl>Private household workers--allocated (1990 internal census)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>415</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors of guards</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>417</catValu>
    <labl>Fire fighting, prevention, and inspection</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>418</catValu>
    <labl>Police, detectives, and private investigators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>423</catValu>
    <labl>Other law enforcement: sheriffs, bailiffs, correctional institution officers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>425</catValu>
    <labl>Crossing guards and bridge tenders</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>426</catValu>
    <labl>Guards, watchmen, doorkeepers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>427</catValu>
    <labl>Protective services, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>434</catValu>
    <labl>Bartenders</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>435</catValu>
    <labl>Waiter/waitress</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>436</catValu>
    <labl>Cooks, variously defined</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>438</catValu>
    <labl>Food counter and fountain workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>439</catValu>
    <labl>Kitchen workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>443</catValu>
    <labl>Waiter's assistant</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>444</catValu>
    <labl>Misc food prep workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>445</catValu>
    <labl>Dental assistants</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>446</catValu>
    <labl>Health aides, except nursing</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>447</catValu>
    <labl>Nursing aides, orderlies, and attendants</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>448</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors of cleaning and building service</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>453</catValu>
    <labl>Janitors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>454</catValu>
    <labl>Elevator operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>455</catValu>
    <labl>Pest control occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>456</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors of personal service jobs, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>457</catValu>
    <labl>Barbers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>458</catValu>
    <labl>Hairdressers and cosmetologists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>459</catValu>
    <labl>Recreation facility attendants</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>461</catValu>
    <labl>Guides</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>462</catValu>
    <labl>Ushers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>463</catValu>
    <labl>Public transportation attendants and inspectors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>464</catValu>
    <labl>Baggage porters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>465</catValu>
    <labl>Welfare service aides</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>468</catValu>
    <labl>Child care workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>469</catValu>
    <labl>Personal service occupations, nec</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>473</catValu>
    <labl>Farmers (owners and tenants)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>474</catValu>
    <labl>Horticultural specialty farmers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>475</catValu>
    <labl>Farm managers, except for horticultural farms</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>476</catValu>
    <labl>Managers of horticultural specialty farms</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>479</catValu>
    <labl>Farm workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>480</catValu>
    <labl>Farm laborers and farm foreman--allocated (1990 internal census)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>483</catValu>
    <labl>Marine life cultivation workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>484</catValu>
    <labl>Nursery farming workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>485</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors of agricultural occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>486</catValu>
    <labl>Gardeners and groundskeepers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>487</catValu>
    <labl>Animal caretakers except on farms</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>488</catValu>
    <labl>Graders and sorters of agricultural products</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>489</catValu>
    <labl>Inspectors of agricultural products</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>496</catValu>
    <labl>Timber, logging, and forestry workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>498</catValu>
    <labl>Fishers, hunters, and kindred</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>503</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors of mechanics and repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>505</catValu>
    <labl>Automobile mechanics</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>507</catValu>
    <labl>Bus, truck, and stationary engine mechanics</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>508</catValu>
    <labl>Aircraft mechanics</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>509</catValu>
    <labl>Small engine repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>514</catValu>
    <labl>Auto body repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>516</catValu>
    <labl>Heavy equipment and farm equipment mechanics</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>518</catValu>
    <labl>Industrial machinery repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>519</catValu>
    <labl>Machinery maintenance occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>523</catValu>
    <labl>Repairers of industrial electrical equipment</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>525</catValu>
    <labl>Repairers of data processing equipment</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>526</catValu>
    <labl>Repairers of household appliances and power tools</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>527</catValu>
    <labl>Telecom and line installers and repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>533</catValu>
    <labl>Repairers of electrical equipment, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>534</catValu>
    <labl>Heating, air conditioning, and refigeration mechanics</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>535</catValu>
    <labl>Precision makers, repairers, and smiths</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>536</catValu>
    <labl>Locksmiths and safe repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>538</catValu>
    <labl>Office machine repairers and mechanics</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>539</catValu>
    <labl>Repairers of mechanical controls and valves</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>543</catValu>
    <labl>Elevator installers and repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>544</catValu>
    <labl>Millwrights</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>549</catValu>
    <labl>Mechanics and repairers, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>558</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors of construction work</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>563</catValu>
    <labl>Masons, tilers, and carpet installers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>567</catValu>
    <labl>Carpenters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>573</catValu>
    <labl>Drywall installers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>575</catValu>
    <labl>Electricians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>577</catValu>
    <labl>Electric power installers and repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>579</catValu>
    <labl>Painters, construction and maintenance</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>583</catValu>
    <labl>Paperhangers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>584</catValu>
    <labl>Plasterers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>585</catValu>
    <labl>Plumbers, pipe fitters, and steamfitters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>588</catValu>
    <labl>Concrete and cement workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>589</catValu>
    <labl>Glaziers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>593</catValu>
    <labl>Insulation workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>594</catValu>
    <labl>Paving, surfacing, and tamping equipment operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>595</catValu>
    <labl>Roofers and slaters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>596</catValu>
    <labl>Sheet metal duct installers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>597</catValu>
    <labl>Structural metal workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>598</catValu>
    <labl>Drillers of earth</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>599</catValu>
    <labl>Construction trades, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>614</catValu>
    <labl>Drillers of oil wells</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>615</catValu>
    <labl>Explosives workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>616</catValu>
    <labl>Miners</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>617</catValu>
    <labl>Other mining occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>628</catValu>
    <labl>Production supervisors or foremen</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>634</catValu>
    <labl>Tool and die makers and die setters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>637</catValu>
    <labl>Machinists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>643</catValu>
    <labl>Boilermakers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>644</catValu>
    <labl>Precision grinders and filers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>645</catValu>
    <labl>Patternmakers and model makers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>646</catValu>
    <labl>Lay-out workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>649</catValu>
    <labl>Engravers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>653</catValu>
    <labl>Tinsmiths, coppersmiths, and sheet metal workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>657</catValu>
    <labl>Cabinetmakers and bench carpenters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>658</catValu>
    <labl>Furniture and wood finishers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>659</catValu>
    <labl>Other precision woodworkers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>666</catValu>
    <labl>Dressmakers and seamstresses</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>667</catValu>
    <labl>Tailors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>668</catValu>
    <labl>Upholsterers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>669</catValu>
    <labl>Shoe repairers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>674</catValu>
    <labl>Other precision apparel and fabric workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>675</catValu>
    <labl>Hand molders and shapers, except jewelers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>677</catValu>
    <labl>Optical goods workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>678</catValu>
    <labl>Dental laboratory and medical appliance technicians</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>679</catValu>
    <labl>Bookbinders</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>684</catValu>
    <labl>Other precision and craft workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>686</catValu>
    <labl>Butchers and meat cutters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>687</catValu>
    <labl>Bakers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>688</catValu>
    <labl>Batch food makers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>693</catValu>
    <labl>Adjusters and calibrators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>694</catValu>
    <labl>Water and sewage treatment plant operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>695</catValu>
    <labl>Power plant operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>696</catValu>
    <labl>Plant and system operators, stationary engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>699</catValu>
    <labl>Other plant and system operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>703</catValu>
    <labl>Lathe, milling, and turning machine operatives</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>706</catValu>
    <labl>Punching and stamping press operatives</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>707</catValu>
    <labl>Rollers, roll hands, and finishers of metal</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>708</catValu>
    <labl>Drilling and boring machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>709</catValu>
    <labl>Grinding, abrading, buffing, and polishing workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>713</catValu>
    <labl>Forge and hammer operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>717</catValu>
    <labl>Fabricating machine operators, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>719</catValu>
    <labl>Molders, and casting machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>723</catValu>
    <labl>Metal platers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>724</catValu>
    <labl>Heat treating equipment operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>726</catValu>
    <labl>Wood lathe, routing, and planing machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>727</catValu>
    <labl>Sawing machine operators and sawyers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>728</catValu>
    <labl>Shaping and joining machine operator (woodworking)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>729</catValu>
    <labl>Nail and tacking machine operators  (woodworking)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>733</catValu>
    <labl>Other woodworking machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>734</catValu>
    <labl>Printing machine operators, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>735</catValu>
    <labl>Photoengravers and lithographers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>736</catValu>
    <labl>Typesetters and compositors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>738</catValu>
    <labl>Winding and twisting textile/apparel operatives</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>739</catValu>
    <labl>Knitters, loopers, and toppers textile operatives</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>743</catValu>
    <labl>Textile cutting machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>744</catValu>
    <labl>Textile sewing machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>745</catValu>
    <labl>Shoemaking machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>747</catValu>
    <labl>Pressing machine operators (clothing)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>748</catValu>
    <labl>Laundry workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>749</catValu>
    <labl>Misc textile machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>753</catValu>
    <labl>Cementing and gluing maching operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>754</catValu>
    <labl>Packers, fillers, and wrappers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>755</catValu>
    <labl>Extruding and forming machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>756</catValu>
    <labl>Mixing and blending machine operatives</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>757</catValu>
    <labl>Separating, filtering, and clarifying machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>759</catValu>
    <labl>Painting machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>763</catValu>
    <labl>Roasting and baking machine operators (food)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>764</catValu>
    <labl>Washing, cleaning, and pickling machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>765</catValu>
    <labl>Paper folding machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>766</catValu>
    <labl>Furnace, kiln, and oven operators, apart from food</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>768</catValu>
    <labl>Crushing and grinding machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>769</catValu>
    <labl>Slicing and cutting machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>773</catValu>
    <labl>Motion picture projectionists</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>774</catValu>
    <labl>Photographic process workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>779</catValu>
    <labl>Machine operators, n.e.c.</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>783</catValu>
    <labl>Welders and metal cutters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>784</catValu>
    <labl>Solderers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>785</catValu>
    <labl>Assemblers of electrical equipment</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>789</catValu>
    <labl>Hand painting, coating, and decorating occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>796</catValu>
    <labl>Production checkers and inspectors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>799</catValu>
    <labl>Graders and sorters in manufacturing</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>803</catValu>
    <labl>Supervisors of motor vehicle transportation</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>804</catValu>
    <labl>Truck, delivery, and tractor drivers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>808</catValu>
    <labl>Bus drivers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>809</catValu>
    <labl>Taxi cab drivers and chauffeurs</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>813</catValu>
    <labl>Parking lot attendants</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>815</catValu>
    <labl>Transport equipment operatives--allocated (1990 internal census)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>823</catValu>
    <labl>Railroad conductors and yardmasters</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>824</catValu>
    <labl>Locomotive operators (engineers and firemen)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>825</catValu>
    <labl>Railroad brake, coupler, and switch operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>829</catValu>
    <labl>Ship crews and marine engineers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>834</catValu>
    <labl>Water transport infrastructure tenders and crossing guards</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>844</catValu>
    <labl>Operating engineers of construction equipment</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>848</catValu>
    <labl>Crane, derrick, winch, and hoist operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>853</catValu>
    <labl>Excavating and loading machine operators</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>859</catValu>
    <labl>Misc material moving occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>865</catValu>
    <labl>Helpers, constructions</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>866</catValu>
    <labl>Helpers, surveyors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>869</catValu>
    <labl>Construction laborers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>874</catValu>
    <labl>Production helpers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>875</catValu>
    <labl>Garbage and recyclable material collectors</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>876</catValu>
    <labl>Materials movers: stevedores and longshore workers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>877</catValu>
    <labl>Stock handlers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>878</catValu>
    <labl>Machine feeders and offbearers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>883</catValu>
    <labl>Freight, stock, and materials handlers</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>885</catValu>
    <labl>Garage and service station related occupations</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>887</catValu>
    <labl>Vehicle washers and equipment cleaners</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>888</catValu>
    <labl>Packers and packagers by hand</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>889</catValu>
    <labl>Laborers outside construction</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>890</catValu>
    <labl>Laborers, except farm--allocated (1990 internal census)</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>905</catValu>
    <labl>Military</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>991</catValu>
    <labl>Unemployed</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>996</catValu>
    <labl>Refused</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>997</catValu>
    <labl>Don't Know</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>999</catValu>
    <labl>Unknown</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Job Tenure &amp; Occupational Mobility Supplement Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="JTRESP" dcml="0" files="ExtractData" intrvl="discrete" name="JTRESP">
  <location EndPos="155" StartPos="154" width="2"/>
  <labl>Eligibility and interview status for Job Tenure Supplement</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[JTRESP identifies individuals who were eligible to be interviewed for the Job Tenure Supplement, and further identifies whether they were interviewed or not.

This variable is part of the Job Tenure Supplement.]]></txt>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>00</catValu>
    <labl>Not eligible</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>01</catValu>
    <labl>Eligible, no interview</labl>
  </catgry>
  <catgry>
    <catValu>02</catValu>
    <labl>Eligible, interviewed</labl>
  </catgry>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Job Tenure &amp; Occupational Mobility Supplement Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
<var ID="JTSUPPWT" dcml="4" files="ExtractData" intrvl="contin" name="JTSUPPWT">
  <location EndPos="165" StartPos="156" width="10"/>
  <labl>Job tenure supplement weight</labl>
  <txt><![CDATA[JTSUPPWT is the Job Tenure Supplement specific weight.  Use JTSUPPWT for analyses using Job Tenure questions.]]></txt>
  <codInstr><![CDATA[CodesJTSUPPWT is a 10-digit numeric variable. In the original data there are two implied decimals in 1983 and 1987, and four implied decimals in samples from 1996 onward. The IPUMS command files automatically make the necessary adjustment, so no further adjustment is needed.]]></codInstr>
  <concept vocab="IPUMS">Job Tenure &amp; Occupational Mobility Supplement Variables -- PERSON</concept>
  <varFormat schema="other" type="numeric"/>
</var>
</dataDscr>
</codeBook>
